

# Victoria Hamilton



lack A This is an old revision of this page, as edited by Ruby2010 (talk | contribs) at 04:05, 27 May 2018 ( $\rightarrow$  Career: remove EL). The present address (URL) is a permanent link to this revision, which may differ significantly from the current revision.

**Victoria Hamilton** (born 5 April 1971) is an English actress. After training at the London Academy of Music and Dramatic Art, Hamilton began her career in classical theatre, appearing in productions with the Royal Shakespeare Company and the National Theatre. In 2002, she appeared in the London stage play A Day in the Death of Joe Egg alongside Clive Owen and later Eddie Izzard.

She made her Broadway debut in 2003 when the production moved to New York, where she earned a Tony Award nomination. She won the Critics' Circle Theatre Award and Evening Standard Theatre Award for her performance in the play Suddenly, Last Summer, held in 2004 at the Lyceum Theatre.

Hamilton has often worked in the costume drama genre. During the 1990s, she had supporting roles in three Jane Austen adaptations: the 1995 serial Pride and Prejudice, the 1995 film Persuasion, and the 1999 film Mansfield Park.

Hamilton won the role of Queen Victoria in the 2001 television production, Victoria & Albert, portraying the monarch in her early years. From 2008 to 2011, Hamilton was a cast member in the BBC1 series Lark Rise to Candleford. Since 2016, she portrays Queen Elizabeth The Queen Mother in the Netflix historical drama series *The Crown*.

Victoria Hamilton				
Born	Victoria Sharp			
	5 April 1971			
	Wimbledon, London,			
	England			
Citizenship	United Kingdom			
Education	London Academy of			
	Music and Dramatic			
	Art			
Occupation	Actress			
Spouse	Mark Bazeley			
Children	2			
Awards	Critics' Circle Theatre			
	Award (2000, 2004)			
	Laurence Olivier			
	Theatre Award (2002,			
	2005)			
	Evening Standard			
	Theatre Award (2004)			

## Career

Hamilton was born in Wimbledon, London to a non-theatrical family. [1][2] She attended St Hilary's School, a private school in Surrey, from 1974–82, then Prior's Field School, Godalming until 1987. [3]

Hamilton initially intended to read English at Bristol University, before opting to train at the London Academy of Music and Dramatic Art. [4][2] She began her acting career in classical theatre, spending the first five years appearing in productions by troupes such as the Royal Shakespeare Company and the National Theatre. [5] She staved with the Royal Shakespeare Company for eighteen months. [6] Hamilton commented in 2001 that it was

"very unfashionable" to begin a career in classical theatre but she had sought to emulate the careers of actors like <u>Judi Dench</u> and <u>Ian Holm</u> who "started in rep and slowly built themselves into the position where they could juggle theatre and film". [2]

### Stage

In 1995, Hamilton appeared in <u>Ibsen</u>'s <u>The Master Builder</u> directed by <u>Peter Hall</u>, starring <u>Alan Bates</u> and <u>Gemma Jones</u> and performed at the <u>Haymarket Theatre</u> in the <u>West End of London</u>. <u>The Independent</u> described Hamilton as a "formidable talent" despite being a newcomer, and noted that she had previously appeared in two performances held at the <u>Orange Tree Theatre</u> in London, one of them being an adaptation of a play by <u>James Saunders</u>. <u>The Master Builder</u> earned Hamilton the <u>London Critics Circle Theatre Award</u> for Most Promising Newcomer. In 2000 she received the <u>Critics' Circle Theatre Award</u> for her performance in <u>As You Like It</u>, Crucible Theatre. <u>[1]</u>

She made her <u>Broadway</u> debut in the 2003 play <u>A Day in the Death of Joe Egg</u>, co-starring alongside the comedian <u>Eddie Izzard</u>. She had starred with <u>Clive Owen</u>, and later Izzard, in a successful London production of the play the previous year, in which she and Izzard portray the parents of a girl with severe brain damage who attempt to save their marriage through jokes and <u>black comedy</u>. For her performance in the Broadway adaptation, Hamilton received a nomination for Tony Award for Best Actress in a Play.

The following year she appeared in <u>Suddenly, Last Summer</u> (2004), an adaptation of the <u>Tennessee Williams</u> play, performed at the <u>Lyceum Theatre</u> in <u>Sheffield.<sup>[11]</sup></u> For her performance, she was honoured as Best Actress by winning the Critics' Circle Theatre Award and <u>Evening Standard Theatre Award</u>. [12][13] Her success lead some of the media to brand her as "the next Judi Dench". [2][14]

She took a three-year break from the stage before returning as  $\underline{\text{Viola}}$  in the Shakespearean comedy  $\underline{\text{Twelfth Night}}$  (2008), staged at Wyndham's Theatre in the West End of London. [14][15]

#### Television and film

Hamilton is known for working in the <u>costume drama</u> genre;  $\frac{[16][17]}{}$  in 2001, she joked that she had been in corsets for the preceding seven years.  $\frac{[18]}{}$ 

During the 1990s, she had supporting roles in three adaptations of <u>Jane Austen</u>'s novels. These include the 1995 serial <u>Pride and Prejudice</u> as Mrs Forster, [19] the 1995 film <u>Persuasion</u> as Henrietta Musgrove, [20] and the 1999 film <u>Mansfield Park</u> as Maria Bertram. [21]

Hamilton won the role of <u>Queen Victoria</u> in the 2001 BBC-TV production <u>Victoria & Albert</u>, despite facing strong competition and being relatively unknown at the time. She auditioned with the director <u>John Erman</u> in a London hotel suite, and after reading lines from several more scenes at his prompting, was offered the part immediately. Noting that the monarch is typically depicted as stern and stout, Hamilton desired to show a younger version who "loved parties and balls and theatre and opera and new dresses" after a childhood spent in a "forbidding environment". [23]

In 2005, Hamilton appeared in the three-part miniseries *To the Ends of the Earth* alongside <u>Benedict Cumberbatch</u> and <u>Jared Harris</u>. The production, an adaptation of the <u>novels of the same name</u> by <u>William Golding</u>, featured various self-absorbed characters who are forced to remain in close quarters while sailing on a

ship to Australia during the <u>Napoleonic Wars</u>. Hamilton described the production as having "some of the most beautiful scripts I've seen", and called her character Miss Granham "one of the strongest people on the boat". [6]

From 2008 to 2011, Hamilton appeared in the <u>BBC1</u> series <u>Lark Rise to Candleford</u> as Ruby Pratt, one of two spinster sisters who run a <u>high fashion</u> shop in a small 19th-century town. [25] <u>The Guardian</u> deemed Ruby's rivalry with her sister Pearl (played by <u>Matilda Ziegler</u>) as a highlight of the series, believing both actresses portrayed their characters with "infectious relish". [26] In 2013, Hamilton played Peggy in the BBC drama series *What Remains*. [27]

In 2015, Victoria starred in the BBC1 Drama, Doctor Foster, playing a character named Anna, a lady who lived across the road from Gemma & Simon Foster, played by Suranne Jones and Bertie Carvel.

In 2016, she appeared in the <u>Netflix</u> series *The Crown* as <u>Queen Elizabeth The Queen Mother</u>. The drama series, which is scheduled to span over six seasons, depicts the relationship between <u>Queen Elizabeth II</u> and <u>Prince Philip</u>, Duke of Edinburgh from 1947 to the present. [28]

In 2017, Victoria reprised her role as Anna in Series 2 of the BBC1 Drama, Doctor Foster, and featured in episodes 1-4 of Series 2, the character had moved away by the final episode.

# Filmography

Year	Film	Role	Notes	Citation
1995	Cone Zone	Zandra Ward	TV film	[1]
	Persuasion	Henrietta Musgrove		[29]
	Pride and Prejudice	Mrs. Forster	TV mini-series (3 episodes)	[29]
1996	The Merchant of Venice	Nerissa	TV film	[29]
1998	King Lear	Cordelia	TV series/Masterpiece Theatre	[29]
1999	Mansfield Park	Maria Bertram		[29]
2000	Midsomer Murders	Hilary Inkpen	TV series (1 episode: "Garden of Death")	[1]
2001	The Savages	Jessica	TV series (6 episodes)	[1]
2001	Victoria & Albert	Queen Victoria	TV serial	[29]
	A Day in the Death of Joe Egg	Sheila	TV film	[29]
2002	Before You Go	Catherine		[29]
	Babyfather	Lucy	TV series (2 episodes)	[29]
	Goodbye, Mr. Chips	Kathie	TV film	[29]
2003	In Search of the Brontës	Charlotte Brontë	TV film	[1]
2005	Twisted Tales	Jessie Vasquez	TV series (1 episode: "The Magister")	[1]
	To the Ends of the Earth	Miss Granham	TV mini-series (2 episodes)	[1]
	A Very Social Secretary	Kimberley Fortier	TV film	[1]
	Jericho	Miss Greenaway	TV series (1 episode: "To Murder and Create")	[1]
2006	Scoop	Jan		[29]
	Wide Sargasso Sea	Cora	TV film	[29]
	The Shell Seekers	Nancy	TV film	[1]
2007	Trial & Retribution	Suzy	TV series (1 episode: "Curriculum Vitae: Part 1")	[29]
	The Time of Your Life	Esther	TV series (6 episodes)	[29]
2008	French Film	Cheryl		[29]

	Lark Rise to Candleford	Ruby Pratt	TV series (25 episodes: 2008–2011)	[29]
2010	Toast	Mum	TV film	[29]
2013	What Remains	Peggy Scott	TV series	[29]
2014	The Game	Sarah Montag	TV series	[29]
2015, 2017	Doctor Foster	Anna	TV series	[30]
2015	Call the Midwife	Iris Willets	TV series	[29]
2016–2017	The Crown	Queen Elizabeth The Queen Mother	TV series	[28]
2016– present	The Circuit	Helene	TV series	[31]

### References

- 1. "Victoria Hamilton profile at" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G2-2588600087.html). Contemporary Theatre, Film and Television. 1 January 2007. Retrieved 7 May 2016 via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- 2. Spencer, Charles (4 December 2001). "Victoria's values" (https://www.telegraph.co.uk/culture/472 6873/Victorias-values.html). *The Daily Telegraph*. Retrieved 1 May 2016.
- 3. "St Hilary's Association" (http://www.sthilarysschool.com/sha). St Hilary's School. Retrieved 13 April 2016.
- 4. "Their awards" (https://www.lamda.org.uk/graduates/their-awards). London Academy of Music and Dramatic Art. Retrieved 13 April 2016.
- 5. Kuchwara, Michael (30 May 2003). <u>"Izzard and Hamilton: A British dynamic duo enchant Broadway" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-74255512.html)</u>. <u>Associated Press</u>. Retrieved 13 April 2016 via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- 6. "To the Ends of the Earth: Interviews with the Cast" (https://www.pbs.org/wgbh/masterpiece/tothee nds/interviews.html). PBS. Retrieved 10 April 2016.
- 7. Taylor, Paul (15 October 1995). "Reviews: Theatre The Master Builder Haymarket Theatre Royal, London" (https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/reviews-theatre-the-master-builder-haymarket-theatre-royal-london-1577869.html). *The Independent*. Retrieved 13 April 2016.
- 8. Isherwood, Charles (4 April 2003). "Putting it together: Matt Wolf charts the road traveled to get Austen actors to the table" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-100484284.html). *Daily Variety*. Retrieved 13 April 2016 via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- "Comedian Izzard to debut on Broadway" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-69319164.html).
   Associated Press. 5 November 2002. Retrieved 13 April 2016 via Highbeam Research.
   (subscription required)
- 10. Wolf, Matt (1 January 2003). "Putting it together: Matt Wolf charts the road traveled to get Austen actors to the table" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-119224271.html). Persuasions: The Jane Austen Journal. Retrieved 13 April 2016 via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- 11. Wolf, Matt (3 June 2004). "Suddenly Last Summer" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-1186869 63.html). *Daily Variety*. Retrieved 13 April 2016 via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- 12. "Mel Brooks's the Producers scoops top theatre award" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-128 007095.html). *Liverpool Daily Post*. 2 February 2005. Retrieved 13 April 2016 via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)

- 13. Singh, Anita (13 December 2004). "Judi Dench honoured for 'doing job I adore' " (https://www.independent.co.uk/arts-entertainment/theatre-dance/news/judi-dench-honoured-for-doing-job-i-adore-686540.html). The Independent. Retrieved 1 May 2016.
- 14. Amer, Matthew (3 December 2008). <u>"Victoria Hamilton" (http://www.officiallondontheatre.co.uk/news/backstage-pass/article/item103455/Victoria-Hamilton)</u>. *Official London Theatre*. Retrieved 1 May 2016.
- 15. Billing, Christian M. (22 September 2009). <u>"Twelfth Night" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1G1-11 8686963.html)</u>. <u>Shakespeare Bulletin</u>. Retrieved 13 April 2016 via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- 16. "What Remains" (https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/profiles/4Rjw35ftmKpYgdNPZpVw1pk/peggy-scott). BBC. Retrieved 7 May 2016.
- 17. Adamson, Judy (27 January 2008). <u>"To The Ends Of The Earth" (http://www.smh.com.au/news/tv-reviews/to-the-earth/2008/01/25/1201157641824.html)</u>. *The Sydney Morning Herald*. Retrieved 7 May 2016.
- Wolf, Matt (16 October 2001). "One Victoria plays another in movie" (https://www.highbeam.com/d oc/1P1-47555354.html). <u>Associated Press</u>. Retrieved 7 May 2016 – via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- 19. "Pride and Prejudice" (https://www.bbc.co.uk/drama/prideandprejudice/characters/pp\_also\_in\_the \_cast\_feature.shtml). BBC. Retrieved 10 April 2016.
- Hinson, Hal (20 October 1995). "Persuasion: Austen found" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-860863.html). The Washington Post. Retrieved 10 April 2016 – via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- 21. Ivry, Bob (17 November 1999). <u>"Taking a clue from Austen" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P1-24051437.html)</u>. *The Record*. Retrieved 10 April 2016 via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- 22. Convey, Olivia (18 August 2001). "Victoria picked for plum role as queen" (https://www.highbeam.c om/doc/1G1-77299600.html). *The News Letter*. Retrieved 12 April 2016 via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- 23. Wolf, Matt (23 October 2001). "Victoria Hamilton, queen share more than a name" (https://www.highbeam.com/doc/1P2-4617821.html). *Chicago Sun-Times*. Retrieved 10 April 2016 via Highbeam Research. (subscription required)
- 24. Parrill 2009, p. 298.
- 25. "Lark Rise To Candleford" (https://www.bbc.co.uk/pressoffice/pressreleases/stories/2007/12\_dece mber/17/lark\_hamilton\_ziegler.shtml) (Press release). BBC. 17 December 2007. Retrieved 20 April 2016.
- 26. Groskop, Viv (11 February 2011). "Lark Rise to Candleford: The end is nigh" (https://www.theguar dian.com/tv-and-radio/tvandradioblog/2011/feb/11/lark-rise-to-candleford). *The Guardian*. Retrieved 12 April 2016.
- 27. Frost, Caroline (9 January 2013). "'What Remains' Episode 2 Review David Threlfall Stars In Intriguing BBC Murder Mystery" (http://www.huffingtonpost.co.uk/2013/09/01/what-remains-review -episode-2-david-threlfall n 3853661.html). *The Huffington Post*. Retrieved 20 April 2016.
- 28. Vincent, Alice; Singh, Anita (11 April 2016). "The Crown: Everything you need to know about Netflix's £100 million series about the Queen's reign" (https://www.telegraph.co.uk/tv/2016/04/11/t he-crown-everything-you-need-to-know-about-netflixs-100-million). *The Daily Telegraph*. Retrieved 20 April 2016.
- 29. "Victoria Hamilton" (http://www.bfi.org.uk/films-tv-people/4ce2bb4168377). British Film Institute. Retrieved 20 April 2016.

- 30. "Doctor Foster Characters" (https://www.bbc.co.uk/programmes/profiles/5JRdFYP2Hb4pZt7cJNNv 54k/characters). BBC. Retrieved 8 May 2016.
- 31. "Channel 4 announces new comedy pilot The Circuit" (http://www.channel4.com/info/press/news/c hannel-4-announces-comedy-pilot-the-circuit). Channel 4. Retrieved 23 August 2016.

#### Works cited

Parrill, Sue (2009). Nelson's Navy in Fiction and Film: Depictions of British Sea Power in the Napoleonic Era (https://books.google.com/books?id=ekt4aEv5dTcC&). McFarland & Company. ISBN 978-0786438556. {{cite book}}: Invalid | ref=harv (help)

## **External links**

Victoria Hamilton (https://www.imdb.com/name/nm0358200/) at IMDb

Retrieved from "https://en.wikipedia.org/w/index.php?title=Victoria\_Hamilton&oldid=843138275"

.